<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A Kilobyte of Helium</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/</link><description>Some thoughts about some things.</description><atom:link href="https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 06:33:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Linux Adventures</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/linux-adventures/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux"&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; in some capacity for over 10 years now, and it's been my primary operating system for about 7.
For the most part, it's served my needs well.
It's also been interesting to watch Linux mature as a desktop OS while Windows has mostly gotten &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; over the same time period.
In this post I want to talk a bit about my journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What even is Linux?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who aren't aware, Linux is one of the major general purpose operating systems, along with Windows and Mac OS.
Linux is extremely prevalent on web servers, and utterly dominates scientific and high-performance computing, but is still pretty marginal on ordinary PCs.
In large part this is because it doesn't come pre-installed on computers made by any major manufacturers, except for a few models targeted at programmers.
Technically, Android and ChromeOS are built on top of Linux, but these are very different products, and it's not helpful to lump them together.
It is also similarly true that Mac OS is built on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkeley_Software_Distribution"&gt;BSD&lt;/a&gt; (another FOSS operating system), and similarly misleading to conflate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple factors that distinguish Linux from its competitors.
The first is that it is free and open source software ("FOSS").
This means that anyone can acquire, modify, and redistribute the source code.
In the past, Linux was mostly developed by volunteers and hobbyists, but nowadays a large proportion of contributions come from corporations that use it as a foundation for various products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second distinguishing factor is that the various parts of the system, such as the Linux kernel (the core of the system) and the graphical and audio subsystems, are independent projects.
These are assembled into complete systems called called "distros" (short for "distribution").
Most of the big distros that you may have heard of, like Ubuntu, Fedora, and Arch, are overwhelmingly similar to each other.
No matter which you use, you're getting the Linux kernel, X.Org or Wayland for graphics, PulseAudio for audio, and so on.
Because of this, which to use mostly comes down to personal preference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the coolest thing about Linux from the user perspective is that there are several completely different graphical interfaces available, called "desktop environments".
Imagine being able to put the Mac interface on your Windows 10 installation, or vice versa.
That's basically the situation with Linux.
If one desktop environment doesn't suit your fancy, you can swap it about for another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Early Experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure exactly when I first discovered Linux, though in high school I had a friend who had it installed on his PS3 (yes, you could do that back then!), along with an old desktop.
Partly inspired by this, I played around with Ubuntu and several other distros using virtual machines, but didn't really do much with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_machine"&gt;virtual machine&lt;/a&gt; is exactly what it sounds like.
Basically, it's a program that you run on your computer like any other, which allows you to run &lt;em&gt;a whole other operating system&lt;/em&gt; inside.
From the perspective of the "guest" operating system, it's just running on ordinary computer hardware, but this is an illusion created by the virtual machine software.
In reality, it's sharing the hardware of the "host" system.
From the user perspective you get get a normal window showing the virtual display.
You can click into it and use your keyboard like any other program, give it pass-through internet access and so on.
The concept is similar to but not exactly the same as an emulator, which simulates a completely different kind of computer (emulators are commonly used for playing old video games on modern computers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The software I was using is called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VirtualBox"&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/a&gt;, and it's still around today.
I highly recommend it as a way of getting your feet wet.
You can install and try out different distros without affecting your current setup, and you can screw around to your heart's content with essentially no risk of damage to the host system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was probably around 2008 when I started doing this.
Linux really wasn't ready for prime time yet, though things were changing rapidly.
I experimented a lot with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubuntu"&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;, then a newcomer, and polished and user friendly that its competitors at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there were a lot of stupid problems.
I remember "not having permission" to use my CD burner.
Thinking myself clever, I opened the command line and used "sudo" command to start the CD burning program as the superuser (=administrator).
This worked, but it also broke the graphical system, and the next time I started the virtual machine I could only log in to the command line.
It turns out you're only supposed to use "sudo" with command line programs (this is a common beginner mistake).
Sure, I was able to fix the problem by Googling, but not being allowed to use your CD burner by default is a pretty stupid design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say, the situation is lot better nowadays.
Actually, things really started to come together within the next couple of years.
Hardware problems were solved, software availability increased dramatically, and
I think this was in part because of the level of community engagement at the time.
Unfortunately, the cloud and mobile revolutions in the mid 2010s soon sucked away attention from desktop computing -- it wasn't "hip" anymore.
Progress has been a lot slower since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linux for Programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In college we used Linux for most of the core computer science classes.
We were taught how to use SSH to log in to a server, and navigate using the terminal (command line), and write our programs in Vim (a hardcore programming text editor).
I kept up with the first two, but gave up on Vim after a semester -- it was just too weird.
Nowadays I could probably make myself learn it, but now I have &lt;a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/"&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/a&gt;, which basically does everything I could possibly ask for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department's Linux workstations and servers all ran &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debian"&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt;.
The only reason I knew this was because of the default desktop background.
Since everything was managed by the department, the choice of distro was more or less irrelevant from our perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like I really got going the first summer I worked as a research assistant for a computer science lab.
I was basically a grunt programmer and IT manager, but it was honestly perfect.
We had a little robot running Ubuntu, and we needed to offload some of the heavy computing to another Ubuntu computer.
Naturally, I did all my work on an Ubuntu workstation as well.
I taught myself how to install and configure all the software we needed.
By the end of the summer, I more or less knew what I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process, I also got used to using Ubuntu for everyday tasks.
I was using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME_2"&gt;Gnome 2&lt;/a&gt; for my desktop environment, the default at the time.
It was basically fine.
The interface was snappy, updates were quick and painless, and I had Firefox, LibreOffice, and Dropbox.
When there was a problem, it was very easy to ask Google what package I needed to install, or what setting to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My understanding is that by this point there were two big issues holding Linux back: (1) hardware compatibility and (2) inability to run most games and commercial software.
My work computer was a generic Dell desktop; if you had a laptop and the WiFi didn't work, then you'd be pretty much out of luck.
Likewise, I had no need for any specific proprietary software at work.
Both of these issues have diminished considerably in the years since then, but I think they are still the two major sticking points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued to use Windows on my personal computer mostly for software reasons, but I installed &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_Mint"&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/a&gt; in a dual-boot configuration for programming.
(Linux Mint is important mainly because of its home-grown desktop interface, Cinnamon, which is really nice.)
Linux provides a way better programming environment than Windows.
Only in the last few years with the second version of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Subsystem_for_Linux"&gt;WSL&lt;/a&gt; has the gap narrowed at all.
In any case, by this point I more or less knew that I'd be able to switch to Linux full time should I feel inclined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goodbye, Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an incident at work while I was teaching English in Japan that prompted me to finally pull the trigger.
My computer decided to reboot and install updates right before I was about to teach a class.
As anyone who has ever used a Windows computer knows, this can take &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;.
I lost precious class time, and I was pissed.
My lessons were not the kind where you could just stop when the bell rang and pick up the next day.
I only saw my kids once a month -- if the day's activity couldn't be finished in 45 minutes then that was it, the end.
But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's possible that I had left to do something and the usual 15 minute countdown appeared---and concluded---while I was gone, or it could have been an irregularity.
The fact of the matter is that this sort of thing is not acceptable.
&lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; will decide whether or not now is an okay time to update my computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By this time Windows 10 was already out, and I knew that this sort of behavior was becoming a matter of policy -- you didn't own your computer anymore.
So, I decided that this would be a good time to try transitioning to Linux.
I started doing all my work on my Linux Mint install, only switching back to Windows when absolutely necessary. which it rarely was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gradually transitioned from Microsoft Office to LibreOffice.
LibreOffice Writer was already quite good, actually superior to Word in many ways.
Calc, the spreadsheet app, was perfectly adequate for my purposes.
Impress, the PowerPoint equivalent, was pretty bad (it still is), but that didn't really matter to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my programs, like Firefox and Dropbox, were already available on Linux, so no change there.
I switched from Notepad++ to Sublime Text, and couldn't be happier.
I really only missed two things: Age of Empires (an RTS game) and Sibelius (music composition software).
Even so, I could boot back into Windows just for those, so who cares.
I already had a desktop at home that only ran Linux Mint, so I was already used to that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that was basically it.
In my day-to-day life, Linux has basically suited me just fine, though there have been a few hiccups.
I'll mention a couple big ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, I experimented with several desktop environments, eventually settling on KDE, which I consider to be the true successor to old-school Windows.
So what was the problem?
Well, the transition from KDE 4 to version 5 was happening around this time, and it was a bit messy.
The first few releases of KDE 5, officially "Plasma 5", were basically unusable, while KDE 4 was no longer being developed, and therefore not receiving any bug fixes and improvements.
Linux Mint, which tracks the LTS (2 year release cycle) version of Ubuntu, was stuck on the frozen KDE 4, while the most recent non-LTS (6 month) releases of Ubuntu had the unusable Plasma 5.
By 2016, though, Plasma 5 was more or less fine, and it has only gotten better and better since then.
Linux Mint discontinued their KDE release, so I stuck with Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem is that Ubuntu started to go down in quality of releases.
For example, in one release they broke Bluetooth, then refused to fix it for "stability" reasons.
You see, in Linux distro world, "stable" doesn't mean "works as intended and doesn't crash"; it means "no changes in functionality".
Never mind the fact that broken software is, well, broken, and therefore useless in its current state.
Anyway, it was a simple matter of installing the bugfix via the lovely Ubuntu &lt;a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/PPA"&gt;PPA&lt;/a&gt; system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think this sounds kind of crappy, well, it is.
But the thing is, if Ubuntu ever becomes intolerable, it's very easy to switch to something else.
If Microsoft, Apple, or Google ruins something for you, you have no recourse; with Linux, you have options.
At the same time, I've been watching what's happening with Windows 8/10/11.
I've had the exquisite displeasure of helping family members troubleshoot and fix the most insane problems--things that never could have happened with Linux, nor with Windows 7--and you know what, I think I'm getting a better deal right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My computer is snappy and responsive despite being 5 years old and only having a dual-core CPU.
My software updates are instantaneous and rarely require reboots; upgrading to the next version of Ubuntu takes minutes, not hours.
Plasma 5 is beautiful, functional, and customizable; Windows 10 is ugly and full of irritating pop-ups, advertisements, and spyware.
I have a list of all my important software and can install almost everything automatically with a single command if I ever need to setup a new computer.
Some of my old games that I play using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine_(software)"&gt;Wine&lt;/a&gt; or in a virtual machine don't work on recent versions of Windows anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and before you suggest that I get a Mac: no.
Apple's computers are overpriced, I hate their keyboards, I hate their operating system, and I still can't play my games without Wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linux for everyone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you might be wondering if I recommend other people to switch to Linux nowadays.
Actually, no, not necessarily.
Linux is ideal for two groups of people: those with very basic needs, who basically spend all their time in a web browser, and power users, who are willing to take the time to learn how to setup and maintain their system.
For everyone else, it depends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, hardware and software compatibility are the big problems.
You can, and should, put Linux on a flash drive and give it a test run (the installer for most distros doubles as a demo system).
If it works well on your computer, great!
If it doesn't work right, and you're not willing to fiddle around to make it work, then that's that.
Likewise if you need MS Office, or the Adobe suite, or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you need to find a desktop environment that suits your preferences.
If you liked Windows 7, then I think you'll love KDE/Plasma.
If you are used to Mac OS, you might prefer Gnome or Cinnamon.
And if the first thing you try isn't quite right, you'll need to experiment, because there are several good options out there.
If this is fun for you like it is for me, then go for it.
But the fact is that a lot of people just don't care that much, and find this to be too much effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there's the problem of choosing a distro.
Again, I'm of the opinion that it doesn't matter that much.
I suggest Ubuntu, not because I'm convinced that it's the best, but because it's available with almost all major desktop environments, and it's popular, so it's easy to get help.
But if you have a friend or family member who can provide you with tech support and they use something different, then maybe try that instead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>linux</category><category>Ubuntu</category><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/linux-adventures/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>cat² = catcat?</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/cat-squared-equals-catcat/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What if I told you that you can do math with language?
What, you didn't think math was about numbers, did you?
Sure, you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do math with numbers, but you can also do math with all sorts of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I'll show you.
We're going to use &lt;em&gt;strings&lt;/em&gt;.
These are just sequences of arbitrary symbols.
Traditionally we the lowercase letters &lt;em&gt;a, b, c, d&lt;/em&gt;, etc., but you could use anything.
I think it would be fun to use little shapes like ♠♣♥♦, but they're too hard to type, so we'll do it the old fashioned way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A string consists of zero or more symbols in linear order.
So &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; is a string, as is &lt;em&gt;ab&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;abcabcaaaaaa&lt;/em&gt;.
There is only one string of length zero, which is called the "empty string".
It's notated ϵ (Greek lowercase epsilon).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can you do with strings?
Well, you can stick them together, one after the other.
The fancy word for this is "concatenatation".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ab&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;cd&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;abcd&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding (concatenating) the empty string to either side of another string just gives you the same string back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abc&lt;/em&gt; + ϵ = ϵ + &lt;em&gt;abc&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;abc&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've even done any kind of programming, this should be familiar.
Programmers are used to the idea of making up new kinds of objects and operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are some other things you can do with strings?
Well, you can repeat a string some number of times.
This is notated with a superscript, like raising a number to a power.
For example, &lt;em&gt;a⁵b⁵&lt;/em&gt; is short for aaaaabbbbb, and &lt;em&gt;(ab)³&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;ababab&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also substitute a string into another.
The notation I've see for this uses a dotted circle (⊙) for this operation, and the string on the left side needs to have a box (□) showing where to insert the string on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;l□r&lt;/em&gt; ⊙ &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;lcr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so what exactly is this good for?
Well, just as you can use numbers to model phenomena in physics or economics, you can use strings to model language.
I'm still thinking about to talk about this in a way that keeps things light and fun, so you'll just have to wait for part two.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>computation</category><category>language</category><category>math</category><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/cat-squared-equals-catcat/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 02:22:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Things I'm Thankful For (2022)</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/things-im-thankful-for-2022/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Technically I'm several weeks late, but really there's never a bad time to spend some time focusing on gratitude.
Here's a few things that I'm feeling thankful for, in no particular order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New friends&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    Let's just say that moving across the country at the height of COVID was not conducive to building a new social network.
    In the last year or so I've finally made a couple of good friends.
    Hopefully there will be many more to come.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New family&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    I have some distant relatives who live in Manhattan.
    They lived out of the country for most of my life, and then I lived out of the country, so I hadn't met them until I moved to the area.
    They're really wonderful people, and it's so nice to be able to stay at their place overnight rather than spending two hours on the train each way just to get half a day in the city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My advisor&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    There's no single person who makes a bigger difference to someone's PhD experience than their advisor, and I found myself a great one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repaved roads&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    The roads where I live are in apalling condition.
    I was foolish enough to buy a commuter bike when you basically need a mountain bike to ride on them.
    But all of a sudden they decided to repave the road I use to get to work, and it's sooo pleasant now.
    Now if they would just redo the road to the grocery store...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free gym&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    My campus gym has its downsides, but it's convenient, and I can get the membership fee reimbursed each year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving health&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    I developed some health problems a few years ago that made life way harder than it should be.
    But things have been slowly getting better, and in the last few months I've been feeling close to normal again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research progress&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    Most PhD students in the U.S. work as teaching or research assistants to fund their education.
    I like teaching, but it's a gigantic time sink, especially when you're still taking classes yourself.
    Fortunately, I've had a position as a research assistant for the last two years.
    It's the only reason I get anything done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acceptance&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    I only came out as gay a couple years ago.
    Fortunately, it's been about as uneventful as one could hope for.
    It's a huge weight off my shoulders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discount baked goods&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    There's almost always something good in my grocery store in the back corner where they put the slightly old bread, cake, pie, and cookies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hot showers&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    There are all sorts of ordinary things that make me really happy, but this is the first that came to mind, so it's the one to round out the list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/things-im-thankful-for-2022/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 02:26:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Song Translation: Kimi no Shiranai Monogatari</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/song-translation-kimi-no-shiranai-monogatari/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the ending song to the anime TV show &lt;em&gt;Bakemonogatari&lt;/em&gt;.
It's a real gem -- beautiful melody and lyrics, and adjusted an octave down it even fits my vocal range!
You can find it on Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often find Japanese song lyrics difficult to understand.
There's a lot of ambiguity as to which lines go together in a way that can greatly change the interpretation, especially if you are not a native speaker.
This one, though, I think I basically understand, which is why I've decided to write it up first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I provide only the romanization and translation below.
You can find the original Japanese &lt;a href="https://www.uta-net.com/song/82447/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
This translation is loose and not matched to the rhythm of the song.
Also, sorry about the weird formatting -- I'm using Markdown tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Title: Kimi no Shiranai Monogatari (The Story You Don't Know) &lt;br&gt;
Lyrics/Composition: ryo &lt;br&gt;
Performer: supercell&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Japanese&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;English&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Itsumodoori no aru hi no koto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;On one completely ordinary day&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kimi wa totsuzen tachiagari itta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;You suddenly stood up and said&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;"Konya hoshi wo mi ni ikou"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;"Let's go stargazing tonight!"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;"Tama ni wa ii koto iu n da ne"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;"Every once in a while you have a good idea!"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nante minna shite itte waratta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;We all said laughing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Akari mo nai michi wo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;While gleefully trapsing down&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Baka mitai ni hashaide aruita&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A completely unlit road&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kakaekonda kodoku ya fuan ni&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;As we tried to supress the anxiety&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oshitsubusarenai you ni&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;That was weighing on us&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Makkura na sekai kara miageta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;We looked up from the blackness&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yozora wa hoshi ga furu you de&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The stars looked as if they might fall from the sky&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Itsu kara darou kimi no koto wo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How long has it been, I wonder&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oikakeru watashi ga ita&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Since I've been chasing after you?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dou ka onegai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Please, I beg you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Odorokanaide kiite yo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Don't freak out when I tell you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Watashi no kono omoi wo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How I feel about you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;"Are ga Denebu, Arutairu, Bega"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;"There's Deneb, Altair, Vega"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kimi wa yubisasu natsu no daisankaku&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I remember you pointing out&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oboete sora wo miru&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The Summer Triangle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yatto mitsuketa Orihime-sama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Look, I found Orihime!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dakedo doko darou Hikoboshi-sama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;But where's her Hikoboshi?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kore ja hitori bocchi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;They'll be lonely like this&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tanoshige na hitotsu tonari no kimi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Laying right beside your cheery self&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Watashi wa nanimo ienakute&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I couldn't utter a word&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hontou wa zutto kimi no koto wo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The truth is that somewhere deep down&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dokoka de wakatteita&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I already knew how I felt about you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mitsukattatte todoki wa shinai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;But I just couldn't say it&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dame da yo nakanaide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No, don't cry&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sou iikikaseta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I told myself&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tsuyogaru watashi wa okubyou de&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I acted like a coward&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kyoumi ga nai you na furi wo shiteta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pretending I had no interest in you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dakedo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And yet&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mune wo sasu itami wa mashiteku&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I felt a sharp pain in my chest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aa sou ka suki ni naru tte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And I realized this is how it feels&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kou iu koto nan da ne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To fall in love&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dou shitai? Itte goran&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tell me, what do you want?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kokoro no koe ga suru&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;My heart called out&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kimi no tonari ga ii&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I want to be with you&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Shinjitsu wa zankoku da&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reality is so cruel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Iwanakatta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I didn't say it&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ienakatta&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I couldn't say it&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nido to modorenai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And now there's no going back&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ano natsu no hi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;That summer night&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kirameku hoshi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The twinkling stars&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ima demo omoidaseru yo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I remember them clearly even now&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Waratta kao mo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I remember your smile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Okotta kao mo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And also your frown&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Daisuki deshita&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I loved them both&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Okashii yo ne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Isn't it strange?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wakatteta no ni&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Even though I knew&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Kimi no shiranai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;You never did know&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Watashi dake no himitsu&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;My secret&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yoru wo koete&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In a distant memory&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tooi omoide no kimi ga&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;From that night&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yubi wo sasu&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;You pointed to the sky&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mujaki na koe de&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;And started to say...&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>music</category><category>translations</category><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/song-translation-kimi-no-shiranai-monogatari/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reflections on Personality</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/reflections-on-personality/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It was probably about 5 years ago that I learned about the Five Factor model of personality.
I'm sure it was mentioned in the intro psychology class that I took years earlier, but anyway this time it stuck.
And it completely changed how I think about people.
It's almost frightening how clearly you can see the five traits once you know what to look for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's pretty easy to find information on this subject, so I'll focus on giving an impression of what the factors are.
No sources cited, so take everything I say with a grain of salt.
I want to keep this blog casual, and give myself a break from the kind of writing I do for my job.
Onward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Big Five&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The five factors are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extroversion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conscientiousness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agreeableness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neuroticism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Openness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these is a continuous variable -- you have some people that score very high, some that score very low, and everything in between.
Also, they are normally distributed, so most people are somewhere in the middle range for each, with the extremes being comparatively rare.
Finally, they are mostly uncorrelated with each other.
This means that any particular individual might have any combination of values for each of the five factors.
So if you wanted to classify people into personality types, and divided each factor into just three levels (low, medium, and high), you would get 3^5, or 243 distinct personality types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems about right to me.
It's hard to place people accurately into a small number of boxes, but at the same time they are not infinitely different from one another.
You can see recurring patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike some of the other schemes you may have heard of (such as the ever popular Myers-Briggs), the Five Factor model actually has a sound scientific basis.
Actually, it's pretty much the only game in town.
The research shows effect sizes larger than almost anything else in all of social science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, I'll describe what each end of the spectrum looks like for each trait, but it's important to remember that most people show a bit of each side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extroversion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental characteristic of extroversion is sensitivity to stimulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extroverts need a lot of stimulation.
This is why they are stereotypically adventurous, thrill-seeking, and above all, sociable.
Humans are social creatures, so social interaction is a particularly good way for extroverts to get their stimulation fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introverts, naturally, are the opposite.
Introverts are strongly effected by external stimuli.
As a result, they don't need as much stimulation to reach a comfortable level, and can easily be pushed beyond this level.
This explains why introverts find socializing tiring.
It's not that they don't need or like it (at least, not necessarily), it's that you can have too much of a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am fairly introverted.
Occasionally I doubt this when I find myself having to take the lead in making small talk or inviting people to do things.
But social interaction &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; tires me out, which more or less cinches it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conscientiousness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most obvious of the five factors.
Conscientious people are neat, organized, and hard-working.
Unconscientious people are, well, not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the five factors actually has two semi-distinct subfactors, which are highly but not perfectly correlated with each other.
I forget what all 10 of the subfactors are, but the two subfactors of conscientiousness, orderliness and industriousness, are clear and memorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orderliness includes the "neat and organized" part.
Orderly people notice things that are dirty, cluttered, or just wrong, and want to fix them.
The way this works is by threshold sensitivity -- a person scoring at level X for orderliness will notice and be bothered by things that for a person at level X+1 simply do not register.
Orderliness is also associated with disgust sensitivity, the main negative emotion that does not correlate with neuroticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Industriousness is the "hard-working" part.
Industrious people work at things diligently even if they are not enjoyable, even if they would rather be doing something else.
If an industrious person feels obligated to do something, they are not likely to half-ass it or quit.
Less industrious people, in comparison, are quicker to throw in the towel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm definitely conscientious, probably about equal in orderliness and industriousness.
What's a bit odd about me is that I aspire to be more conscientious than I actually am.
My room, for example, is often in a state that I would describe as an "organized mess".
Everything has a place, but it's not exactly pretty, and wow, it's kind of dusty, and those papers really should be cleaned out.
Similarly, I have a certain amount of trouble getting things done.
I frequently make plans and checklists, then proceed to completely ignore them.
Ultra-organized people impress me more than anything.
Who knows, maybe all conscientious people are secretly like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Agreeableness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreeableness is basically niceness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreeable people want to get along with others, and are concerned for their happiness and well-being.
The former means that they tend to be polite, and avoid "rocking the boat".
The latter leads to nurturing and self-sacrificing behavior, and being deeply invested in personal relationships.
Disagreeable people, in contrast, could care less what others think or feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, it turns out that agreeableness is &lt;em&gt;inversely&lt;/em&gt; correlated with competitiveness.
Disagreeable people are usually very competitive, while agreeable people usually are not.
What's probably going on is that it is the nurturing aspect of agreeableness that is the opposite of competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I'm fairly agreeable, though there's a bit of ambiguity on this one.
I can also be very blunt, which is not supposed to be typical of agreeable people.
I have a theory for this, but it's too vague to try to explain here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Neuroticism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuroticism is general sensitivity to negative emotions: sadness, anxiety, anger, guilt, etc.
Everything except for disgust, as mentioned earlier.
Neurotic people are more likely than non-neurotic to get upset when bad things happen, and to get &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; upset when &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; bad things happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a bit strange compared to the other traits, in that high neuroticism seems to be mostly a bad thing.
For example, high neuroticism is associated with risk of clinical anxiety and depression.
This certainly seems maladaptive, since these conditions generally make it &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt; to deal with one's problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who is moderately neurotic, I would speculate that the benefit of negative emotions is that they can serve as a wake-up call when things are amiss.
For example, I get pretty upset with myself when I think I screwed up somehow, more so when I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that I screwed up.
This is a pretty strong motivator to never make the same mistake again.
Life is probably easier for non-neurotic people, but there are downsides to being too happy-go-lucky as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Openness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Openness includes both openness to ideas and openness to experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open people are interested in learning and doing new things, including but not limited to creative pursuits like art and music.
What draws them in is not popularity or practicality, but the intrinsic fascination of the the thing itself.
They are also inclined to change their beliefs when presented with new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-open people are more comfortable with what they already know.
They are less likely to see the value in the new and different -- what's wrong with the way we've always done things?
They also tend to be resistant to changing their beliefs, even when presented with strong evidence.
Maybe they'll come around eventually, but maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As will probably come as no surprise, I'm very high in openness.
I'm doing a PhD after all -- it's kind of a prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extroversion + Openness - Neuroticism = Adventurousness?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's really cool about the Five Factor model is that you can see how the different personality traits interact.
For example, introverted people are not necessarily shy, but people who are both introverted and neurotic are likely to be.
Similarly, conscientiousness plus neuroticism is a recipe for perfectionism.
Low conscientiousness and high openness, plus maybe a dash of agreeableness, makes a hippy, the opposite, a prude.
Extroversion plus agreeableness is that person who is super bubbly and nice to everyone.
Disagreeableness and low openness is that insufferable jackass whose actions can't possibly be wrong.
Don't take my word for it though -- pay attention and see what you can pick out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Are there good and bad personality types?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that each side of each individual trait probably has its advantages and disadvantages.
For example, it might seem like high agreeableness is basically a good thing, but it's not that simple.
Agreeable people have a tendency not to stand up for themselves, and extremely high agreeableness makes makes people susceptible to abuse.
Also recall the idea about neuroticism I mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for combinations of traits, I think that high agreeableness and openness help to ameliorate some of the negative aspects of other personality traits, especially when it comes to dealing with other people.
Openness helps you understand that not everyone is like you, and agreeableness provides motivation to try to get along.
On the other hand, the opposite values make things much worse (what I called the jackass type above).
From the perspective of a person like this, they are obviously right and you are wrong, and who gives a damn what you think anyway.
This has been on my mind a lot lately, due to dealing with a person who is pretty extreme in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Can you change your personality?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is basically "no".
While personality, like many things, develops from the interaction of genetics and individual experience, by the time you are an adult your personality is basically set.
This might be disappointing, but it's not all doom and gloom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, simply understanding your personality can make it possible to leverage your strengths while compensating for your weaknesses, and the clear picture provided by the Five Factor model helps a lot with this.
It is possible, with effort, to build habits that go against your natural instincts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, personality is not the entirety of who you are.
Your knowledge and beliefs about the world are important too.
So, for example, if you are neurotic, one of the things you can do to make life easier is to at least try to avoid getting upset when nothing is wrong.
Hardly anyone noticed that flub during your presentation, and they won't remember anyway.
No, that person probably doesn't hate you, they're probably just stressed.
And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don't take it personally&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking a lot about personality lately, so I'll probably have more to say in the future.
Until then!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>personality</category><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/reflections-on-personality/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hello, World!</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/hello-world/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I thought it might be fun to try blogging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend recently, and he vouched for the value of keeping a journal. I agreed with him. In fact, I was convinced of the value of journaling when I was 18. Many years later, I've never succeeded at making it a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogging is something else I've never done. Maybe this will stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're wondering about the title, it's intended to be meaningless...mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you around!&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/hello-world/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2022 04:19:38 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>