<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A Kilobyte of Helium (Posts about miscellaneous)</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/categories/cat_miscellaneous.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 06:45:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Talent and the Lack Thereof</title><link>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/talent-and-the-lack-thereof/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am distinctly untalented at playing music.
This is a fact that I'm quite convinced of, yet on several occasions when I've tried to express it to people I know I've been met with a lot of skepticism.
If you heard me play, you probably wouldn't believe me either.
But it's true: I do not have a talent for musical performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I play two instruments, piano and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marimba"&gt;marimba&lt;/a&gt; (a keyboard percussion instrument, like a big xylophone).
I've played the piano since 3rd grade.
I wasn't particularly good at it as a child, and didn't put much effort into it until I was about 17.
To give an idea of my level, I can play the first movement of Beethoven's Pathetique Sonata.
This is not a hard piece.
On a scale from 1 to 10, with 1 being "child's play" and 10 being "if you can play this you can play anything", it's maybe a 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, it would be more accurate to say that I can &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; play Mvt. I of Pathetique.
I practiced this piece for hundreds of hours over the course of about 10 years, and I still can't quite play it properly.
I can barely maintain the left hand tremolo that accompanies the second (fast) theme.
I make constant flubs even when I'm well practiced.
And there are a couple places where I simply can't execute the notes in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be absolutely clear, this is not just about Beethoven's Pathetique.
I have the same problems with other pieces: I don't have the dexterity to pull off technical maneuvers consistently, or at all in some cases, and even the easy stuff I frequently screw up.
As for the marimba, for now let's just say my level of skill is comparable to my piano playing: I can play real, non-trivial pieces, but it's a massive struggle, and it took thousands of hours just to be passible.
Basically, I am lacking in physical coordination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this only scratches the surface of what it means to perform music.
I am also pretty bad at the expressive aspect, both in knowing what to do and in implementing it when I do have an idea in my mind for how I want the music to sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some things I do seem to be good at.
I'm decent both at reading music off the page and also at memorizing it.
My sense of rhythm is not bad for a keyboardist, though pretty poor for a percussionist.
And I think I can &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; classical music to some extent.
It's hard to explain, but it kind of "makes sense" to me in a way that I think not everyone can relate to.
But none of these skills are really exceptional, merely above average, and they're not enough to make up for my deficits -- there is no world in which I could have become a musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind you, this doesn't bother me all that much.
In fact, I'm rather proud of my musical accomplishments precisely because what I know that they are solely due to my own hard work.
Scott Alexander has a wonderful &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/01/31/the-parable-of-the-talents/"&gt;essay&lt;/a&gt; on this topic.
Also, I enjoy playing, and indeed, practicing music.
It's a bit like weight-lifting: it's uncomfortable, but not altogether unpleasant, and you gain endurance over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are things that I am talented at, things that came naturally to me.
Music is not one of them, and that's okay.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>music</category><category>piano</category><category>talent</category><guid>https://www.kilogramofhelium.net/posts/2022/talent-and-the-lack-thereof/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 05:03:57 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>